How often should your
videos perform above average?
Well, a while back,
I analyzed 40 world
-class channels over the
course of a two
-year period. And these
were channels with massive
credibility, full -time editors,
researchers, analysts, strategists, big
production budgets. And what
I found is seven
out of 10 of
their videos performed average
or below, and only
three broke out past
their average and noticeably
grew the channel. So
let that sink in.
These are world -class
creators with potentially decades
of experience. So why
is it that everyone
freaks out when they
post a video and
it's ranked a six
out of 10? Like
that's a failure. Well,
it's not your fault
because that one out
of 10 ranking system
YouTube gives you when
you post a video
designed to gamify the
system so that you
get addicted to trying
to get YouTube more
views because that's how
they make their money.
But it's one of
the least useful metrics
for anyone trying to
build a business. In
fact, it could cause
you to waste time
on content that never
grows your business. But
not only is that
an awful part of
the YouTube studio, I
also get people going,
Ed, why is my
click -through rate so
low? Help me. I
don't look at click
rates or any data
in the YouTube studio
pretty much at all.
And I still have
multiple simple play buttons
and millions of views.
So in this video,
I'm gonna show you
the basics of measurement.
You're gonna learn what
to care about, the
mistakes to avoid, and
I'm gonna show you
how to actually measure
if a video is
a flop or a
hit for you. And
this is gonna do
three things. It's gonna
improve your mindset because
you're probably doing it
for a reason. It's
gonna help you do
way better than you
think with your channel.
It's gonna give you
a repeatable system to
find what's working and
build on it fast.
It's gonna help you
learn lessons that matter.
And then after that,
I'm gonna give you
a more detailed measurement
system for every video
you make. All right,
so let's start with
the first thing you
need to be able
to measure a video
success. So if I
said to you, I'm
gonna give you 10
grand if you win
the race, you'd be
like, cool. And you
start running, but a
few miles in, you'd
suddenly go, hang on,
where's the finish line?
How do I even
win this thing? Then
what would happen is,
you would just keep
running. You would lose
motivation because you have
no expectation for how
long this race could
take you. And then
you'd feel like you
were making no real
progress. YouTube is the
same. People post a
video, open the YouTube
studio, see the ranking
and immediately react very
emotionally. Why is this
an eight out of
10? This one flopped.
Do I need a
better title? Maybe I
should start a TikTok
and get my billion
views from my loyal
fans in the Congo
so I feel better
about myself. And this
happens because they didn't
set their expectations for
what they thought would
happen or even set
an end goal to
measure by, meaning they
get totally lost. So
the first thing you
need to do when
making a video is
set your expectations before
you post and pick
your goal, which is
why it's the top
thing on every planner
I made you. So
here's how to set
expectations for a video.
The first thing you
need to do is
understand there are different
levels of risk for
every video you make.
So have a look
at this chart. If
you are repeating a
proven format that has
already worked on your
channel, you can expect
an above average performance
for it, meaning above
a six out of
10 on your one
out of 10 ranking.
Now, this is a
lower risk video because
when viewers know you
for a format or
a title or a
topic, that's their expectations
they want meeting again
for your channel. And
hopefully you've realized finding
these videos and repeating
over and over again
is the name of
the game by now.
If not, my gosh,
you need help. I've
literally said it in
every video. Now, after
that, if you're trying
something that worked on
another channel in your
niche or an adjacent
one, AKA an outlier,
the thing we built
our entire Patent Bank
on, that's medium risk.
And my expectations for
its performance would be
it's more likely to
perform in your bottom
four than your top
because it worked elsewhere,
but that doesn't mean
it will work for
you. It's a test
that we're failing as
fast as we can
to establish. So one
creator might have built
their channel on listicles
that only appeal to
like a beginner audience
and your channel might
have been built on
deep dives, which don't.
So when you test
this out, you're potentially
going against what your
viewers might want. So
anytime I try a
new style of video
on my channel, even
if it's based on
outliers, I expect below
six out of 10
in the ranking, but
it's still important we
try this because we
only need it to
work once before we
then have another repeatable
format we can do,
which will lift our
entire channel. And then
the last thing that's
incredibly high risk is
if you're just making
a video without any
research where you're like,
I just think I
want to make this
because I think it's
a good idea. I
would expect that to
always be a 10
out of 10 flop.
And that is sadly
why most people never
grow a channel because
they do that over
and over again, which
I'm telling you now
is never going to
work. It might work
one in every million
before you go, it
worked for me. So
before every video you
make, you have to
set some expectations to
measure by, which should
be that three out
of 10 times, this
is probably not going
to work for you.
If you don't repeat
something that's worked on
the channel, it's probably
not going to work
for me. And if
you put a ton
of effort into this,
it's 70 % likely
not to work for
you. Okay, so once
you've got those expectations,
you pick a goal
that ties into it.
So if you remember
from your planning phase,
every video should be
optimized for either views,
sales or emails. And
it's very unlikely we
can get all three
of those to work
at once. So I
just pick one that
I'm most bothered about.
And then I make
sure the video ticks
all the boxes to
hopefully achieve it. Anything
else that happens there
is a bonus. When
you have that goal
and expectations, you can
now successfully measure against
them. So let's talk
about how to track
views based on those
expectations and goals in
a useful way, because
pretty much everyone does
this in a way
that sets them up
for the staircase of
pain, being 10 times
more painful than it
needs to be. And
actually meaning they can
never get off it.
All right, so what
I want you to
do is think about
YouTube like this. You
already know that even
for the best channels
in the world, only
three in 10 videos
perform above average. So
expecting every video to
be in your top
three is very, very
unrealistic. So to avoid
feeling like you're failing
and to measure properly,
we measure views by
the middle. What does
that mean? Well, you
look at where your
videos rank against spots
five and 10 in
this one of 10
board. And if it
lands position six or
higher, that's a win
because you've just replaced
one of your old
middle performers and raised
your channel average. So
let's say your position
five video gets 500
views. Then you post
the video that gets
600 and that 600
views becomes your new
position five. If you
keep hitting new five
of 10s, every time
your middle shifts from
500 to a thousand
views and your entire
channel on how well
optimized your sales system
is now 200 %
more effective because your
middle doubled. The YouTube
one of 10 board
only really makes it
clear when you've got
an outlier, not when
you're raising your channels
average views bit by
bit, which was the
most important bit. That
is the bit that
generates the sales, not
the cold outliers. So
you need to celebrate
beating the middle consistently
because this creates sustainable
growth, not short -term
spikes. And just as
importantly, this approach protects
your mindset from the
emotional burnout you're gonna
feel. But here's another
thing about the one
of 10 board. Most
creators, they look at
their one of 10
dashboard and they panic
when a video ranks
eighth, ninth or 10th.
But firstly, if your
one of 10 has
a thousand views and
your 10 of 10
has 900 views, you
do not have a
one of 10 board.
A mouse could sneeze
in the outer Hebrides
and YouTube could suddenly
give it a bunch
of impressions that makes
your 10 out of
10 a one out
of 10. That is
not a big enough
spread. That's actually impressive.
So look at mine.
My one of 10
here has 88 ,000
views to 8 ,000.
So with a 10X
split. So you only
have a one of
10 board when the
top video has significantly
more views than the
bottom. Otherwise, they're all
ranked the same. But
also you actually want
a massive gap like
I have. It's really
important because look, the
top videos clearly show
this worked, do more
of this. The bottom
videos clearly show this
flopped, do less of
that. So this couldn't
give you a more
obvious sign of what
to repeat and what
to do more of.
So if your one
of 10 board has
a tiny difference, you're
very likely second guessing
everything. So just stop
obsessing over it. It's
not really that useful.
All right, so now
that we've covered how
to react to YouTube
view performance using the
one of 10 board,
let's move into measuring
business results and the
metrics that can actually
make you more money.
So these metrics matter
way more than views
to me because they
directly grow your business,
not make YouTube ad
revenue. Also the business
metrics are a much
clearer sign of how
impactful and useful your
content was for your
target buyer, where the
views are not. And
the good news is
you don't need a
million views to make
a great income. You
just need a video
that converts. So here's
how to measure the
business side of performance.
And then to do
that, we're going to
use RevTrack. If you
don't have RevTrack, this
can still work for
you. It just requires
much more of an
educated guess rather than
just looking at quick
raw data. So firstly,
measure everything at the
seven day mark. So
why do we measure
by the seven day
mark? Well, it will
have given us enough
data to start off
with because many of
you won't have much
in the first day,
but also it's telling
us when our hot
returning viewers are taking
actions. And those are
the people that we've
been nurturing over time.
It's very unlikely that
a new cold audience
just jumps in and
buy your stuff and
cold audiences massively dilute
your data and they'll
make it feel like
you're not doing as
well. So when I'm
tracking on day seven,
there's a few things
I look at. Link
clicks, email signups from
the video, sales from
the video, waitlist signups
for video, calls booked
from the video. Now
you might not have
a waitlist or a
call booking thing. That's
fine if you don't,
but let's move on
to look at how
to analyze some of
these key ones that
most of us will
have starting with link
clicks. So we've tracked
over half a billion
views using RevTrack up
until the time of
filming this and discovered
that this is actually
the most important business
metric, because let's say
your average video drives
1 % of your
viewers to click on
the link below it.
If you increase that
to 4%, that's not
a 3 % increase.
That's a 400 %
increase. So 400 %
increase is a 4
% increase. So 100
% more people than
average go to your
sales page or email
signup. What that means
is the link below
one of your videos
is one of the
highest leverage pieces of
data in our entire
system. And it's really
easy to increase too.
So the video about
conversion optimization in the
planning module taught you
how to increase this.
I'm not gonna go
over it again, but
not everyone knows how
important the link click
is. So when you
post a video on
day seven, anything above
the middle performance for
link clicks from your
RevTrack is good. Anything
in the top two,
is gonna teach you
a massive lesson you
wanna repeat and anything
below the middle, don't
do again. If you
don't have RevTrack, you
can't really track link
clicks in this way.
But what you can
do is just look
at the traffic to
the page in the
seven days when you
posted it and then
track that. Now, if
there's traffic coming to
that page from lots
of different places, the
data is gonna be
muddied. And we're not
gonna know if that
traffic is caused by
the video or other
things, but it could
still be useful. Next,
we have email signups.
Again, we measure by
the middle on day
seven and ask, why
did this video get
better results than this
one? And then we
do the same. We
repeat more of what
worked and less of
what didn't and celebrate
anything above the middle.
Don't worry, later on
in this module, I'm
gonna give you questions
that you ask to
help work out why
things performed the way
they did or why
they didn't. But you
do need to be
very careful looking at
this data because look,
that's YouTube telling me,
Ed, your viewers hated
this video, never make
it again with a
10 or 10 flop.
And then that's RevTrack
telling me, Ed, this
was so good for
email signups, do whatever
the heck you did
again. So, that's what
I'm gonna do. And
then I'm gonna do
this. So, that's what
I'm gonna do. And
then I'm gonna do
this. This is why
tracking these metrics is
critical because YouTube is
going to get you
to do what makes
them money, not you.
In your landing page
builder, you can look
at the email signups
for the week. If
you posted a video
that week, you'll likely
see an increase in
email signups. It's just
not quite as accurate
as using RevTrack. So,
the next thing we
track on the seven
day mark is sales.
And this is where
most people panic. But
the reality is a
video can have average
views and still make
a lot of money
because conversion content is
often more specific to
less people, more serious
people. And that is
what will make you
more money. And if
you're not tracking what
videos make you money,
you can't optimize your
channels for sales or
point content back to
high converting videos. So,
it's critical. And again,
all you do is
when this data loads,
you measure by the
middle. And if the
video is above average,
ask why. And if
it's below, ask why
and just repeat what
worked. And then for
sales, if you don't
have RevTrack, you'll just
need to look at
the week sales and
know them. But if
there's multiple traffic, if
there's multiple traffic sources
going to the page,
then the data is
not as accurate. So,
you kind of want
to look at, did
the average sales increase
that week? If so,
it could be the
video. Seeing the pattern
here, right? This data
is so much more
simple than the YouTube
studio, right? And just
remember a one of
10 for sales and
a 10 of 10
for views doesn't matter
because sales is the
most important metric. And
we can always point
more end screens back
at this video. So,
please don't panic. So,
that's the basic idea
behind measurement. Have expectations,
a goal, measure by
the middle, and then
repeat what worked to
grow the business if
you want sales and
emails, and then repeat
what works to get
views if you just
want more views. Don't
expect many videos to
do all three. I've
got about four that
did amazing for all
of them at once,
but that's four in
a lot of videos.
All right, now, before
we move on to
the measurement system, I
just want to run
over one more myth.
And this is something
that really confuses people
and causes them to
procrastinate and waste a
lot of time mucking
around in the YouTube
studio, making changes they
don't need to. So,
people come to me
and they say, Ed,
my watch time dropped
help, or Ed, my
click -through rates dropped,
but here's what you
need to understand. Click
-through rate goes down
when you get more
views from cold viewers,
and views go up
when you reach more
cold viewers. So, your
click -through rate can
look worse, but if
your video is getting
more traffic, it doesn't
matter. It's the same
with watch time. And
I spoke about this
in the earlier modules,
but I have to
bring it up again.
So, what happens is
people come to me
and they're trying to
fix their click -through
rate when it doesn't
need fixing. It's actually
doing quite well. But
also, I don't look
at click -through rate.
I don't look at
any of this data.
All I look at
is, did this video,
meet my expectations or
miss them, and did
it hit my views,
email, or sales goal?
Okay, so now you
understand the basics of
measuring, let's go one
level deeper in the
next video to show
you exactly where to
measure to then base
your decisions on and
to learn lessons from.